THIS STORY IS A FICTION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES AND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、组织名均为虚构）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（与任何特定事件或现象无关）
-Yeah. -I think so.
-对 -我也这么觉得
He's very suspicious!
他很可疑
Then there's a new problem, right?
那就衍生了新的问题 对吧？
Alcohol… Bring me more alcohol…
酒 再拿酒来…
He's changed so much.
他变了好多
Looking at his face makes alcohol taste bad.
但看到他的脸 酒都变难喝了
I agree completely.
我也深有同感
Huh? Thanks…
哦 不好意思啊…
How long are you going to sulk like that?
您打算闷闷不乐到什么时候？
I'm not sulking.
我没有闷闷不乐
Please don't forget, you're at work right now.
请别忘了您还在工作中
I get it.
我知道
He doesn't get it.
你才不知道
A man like Sir Jinshi does not respond like a child like that.
名为壬氏的人物 不会如此孩子气地回话
get attached to his toys like that.
不会如此执着于他的玩物
Here's more work for you.
新的工作来了
That day, I struggled in getting details of what happened from Concubine Gyokuyou.
那天费了一番功夫 才从笑得乐不可支的玉叶妃那儿
-She couldn't stop laughing. -A misunderstanding?
误会？
She explained the payment for the surety was a meeting with a popular courtesan.
原来做保人的谢礼
To think that that girl had such connections…
没想到那姑娘会有这等人脉
And what sorts of things did my master imagine?
不知道主子又会因此有何想象
Youth is a scary thing.
年轻真是可怕
But to think that he finished his work so quickly so that
但他那样火速地将公事处理完
he could go meet the girl,
满心欢喜地要去见那姑娘
only to learn she had gone home with another man…
结果对方却和不知名的男人回老家了
It must've been quite the shock.
的确是有如晴天霹雳一般吧
Why can't they use their heads a little more?
他们真该多用点脑筋思考
Many bureaucrats try to propose laws that only benefit them.
有许多官员 都想通过为自己图利的法案
I do feel pity that his workload is increasing from such nonsense.
为了这些无聊的法案而工作量大增 看了实在让人不忍心
Sir Jinshi!
壬氏大人
Work hours have ended. Can't this wait?
公务时间已过 你之后再来吧
No, this isn't about work. The thing is…
不 这非关公务 是…
Sir Kounen is…?
浩然大人吗？
-Sir Jinshi. -Let's go, quickly!
-壬氏大人 -快走吧
Oh, my. That's terrible news…
那真是太不幸了
Apparently, some high-up bureaucrat has died.
听起来是某位高官过世了
This may be a bit harsh,
或许有些冷淡
but I'm not so sentimental as to mourn someone who's a complete stranger.
但对于连长相和名字都不知道的人 我实在没有感伤到能同情对方
He was in his fifties, and the cause of death
这个人约年过五十
was over drinking.
死因据说是饮酒过量
He brought this onto himself.
完全是自作自受
But if this person
但这位大人
went out of his way to get the head lady-in-waiting to leave, then…
既然特地用别的事情 支开了侍女长 也就是说…
Apothecary. Do you really think the cause of death was alcohol?
药师 你觉得死因 真的是饮酒过量吗？
I knew he would ask that.
果然问了
Anyone who enjoys alcohol
喜欢喝酒的人
would know that drinking too much is bad for your body.
应该都知道喝多了会中毒
Over-drinking for many years causes your organs to deteriorate.
长年饮酒会损害脏腑
Drinking a large amount at once could cause death in some cases.
若一口气喝下大量的酒 因此而死亡也是有可能的
I heard that he was at a banquet and drank a large amount of alcohol.
我听说他是在和朋友的宴会中 喝了大量的酒
In that case, he would die.
那样的确会死
But Sir Kounen holds his liquor well.
但浩然大人的酒量很好
I don't believe he died from over drinking.
我不认为他会死于饮酒过量
The dead man's name was Kounen.
死去的男子名叫浩然
He was a vivacious soldier who could chug an entire bottle,
是能将整坛酒一饮而尽的豪爽武将
and he was well-liked.
人品似乎也很不错
-Gaoshun. -Yes, sir.
-高顺 -是
This is the alcohol he was drinking at the banquet.
这是当时他在宴会喝剩下的酒
Alright, alcohol!
好耶 有酒
The bottle containing Sir Kounen' drink.
浩然大人喝的酒
It was knocked over and all of it spilled out.
因为打翻弄破 所以全洒了
So we wouldn't know if that bottle contained poison.
那么也无从得知 酒瓶里的酒是否有毒了呢
Exactly.
正是如此
He's lacking energy today. He probably knows he's asking for a lot again.
他今天很谦和呢 是因为知道这些要求强人所难吗？
He should be his usual glittering self.
平常那种光彩夺目的样子 还比较适合他
These days, I can't help but see Sir Jinshi
这阵子的壬氏大人
as much more child-like than he used to be.
总觉得比起从前更像个孩子
There's a mix of sweet and salty flavors.
甜味和咸味混在一起
It tastes like someone added salt to an originally sweet alcohol…
尝起来像是在 原本有甜味的酒里加了盐巴
-What's wrong? -It has a unique taste.
-有什么问题吗？ -有个奇特的味道
Yes. It's sweet, right?
对 是甜的吧？
It's what Sir Kounen liked.
浩然大人喜欢这种酒
He loved sweets more than anything.
他最爱甜的东西了
He wouldn't touch even the most expensive smoked meats or rock salts.
就算准备了上等的熏肉或岩盐 他也是完全不碰的
I see.
这样啊
He used to like spicy things, but he said
他以前喜欢吃辣
he suddenly developed an appetite for sweet things.
但某天他突然说爱上甜食了
Even his meals were mostly sweet.
就连饮食都几乎做成甜的口味
That would cause diabetes.
那会得糖尿病呢
Don't bring my memory back to reality.
别把我从回忆拉回现实啊
-You're still drinking? -Spice-lover turned sweet-lover, huh?
-是说你还想喝啊？ -嗜辣的人转而嗜甜了吗？
Was there salt at this banquet?
宴会的料理有盐吗？
Yes. They served rock salt, moon cakes, and dried meats.
有 似乎有岩盐、月饼和肉干
Should I prepare the same things?
要准备同样的东西吗？
No. I'll finish drinking before it's ready.
不必 还在准备时我就会喝完了
That's not what I was….
我不是这个意思…
Can we get our hands on the bottle Sir Kounen was drinking from?
能弄到浩然大人 用来喝酒的那个瓶子吗？
It's shattered into pieces.
都成了碎片了
It doesn't matter.
没关系
There's another thing I want you to look into.
还有另一件事想请您调查
Excuse me.
打扰了
-Here's the report. -Thank you very much.
-报告在这儿 -非常感谢
I knew it.
果然
This is the bottle.
这就是那个酒瓶
Is it okay to lick it?
舔了不会有事吗？
There's no poison in here.
酒瓶里没有毒
It's salt?
是盐吗？
Precisely. You mentioned, Sir Jinshi,
正是 壬氏大人您说过
that Sir Kounen suddenly developed a liking for sweet things.
浩然大人某天突然变得喜爱甜食
-And he only ate sweets after that. -Yes.
-而且在那之后就只吃甜食 -对
But in this bottle has so much salt that there are grains leftover
但看来酒瓶中的酒含有大量的盐
after it has dried.
甚至在干掉后还留下了盐粒
Salt is a necessary ingredient for the human body,
虽然盐对人体不可或缺
but too much, and it becomes poison.
但食用过量也会毒害身体
So the cause of death was…
所以死因是…
Considering how much he drank,
考虑到他所喝的酒量
and how much salt was dissolved in the drink,
和掺在酒里的盐量
this could very much be the cause of death.
说这就是死因也不奇怪
But if he drank
不过 他要是喝下
something this salty, wouldn't he notice the taste…
这么咸的东西 一般都会察觉吧
He didn't notice. Please take a look at this.
他并未察觉 请看这个
These are the records of Sir Kounen's lifestyle habits.
这上面记载了浩然大人的生活习惯
Looking at this, my guess is that Sir Kounen
照这内容来看 恐怕浩然大人
lost the ability to taste salt.
变得尝不出咸味了
There's no way…
怎么可能…
I learned that Kounen
浩然这名男子
was a diligent and talented bureaucrat,
据说是一名认真有才的官员
who lived a monastic life.
并且有着严以律己的个性
And many years ago,
在多年前
he lost his wife and child to an epidemic disease.
他的妻子和孩子 因为疫病的关系而过世
After that, all he did was work.
在那之后 他就埋首于工作中
His only place of joy was in alcohol and sweets.
唯一的乐事就是酒和甜食
There is an illness where one loses their sense of taste.
有种疾病会让人丧失味觉
Causes include an imbalanced diet or stress.
病因可能是饮食不均、身心压力
Diligent people often suppress their emotions.
越是认真的人 越会压抑内心
and that burden can lead to illness.
那种压抑造成的负荷迟早会转化为病
So who placed the salt in the alcohol bottle?
那么 是谁把盐加进酒瓶里的？
It's not my job to investigate that.
那部分的调查 就不是我的工作了
However, there was salt added to yesterday's alcohol as well.
不过 昨天拿到的酒也掺了盐
It could be someone who didn't like sweet drinks
有可能是喝不习惯甜酒的人
added the salt from the banquet.
将作为料理的盐加了进去
Or… There are many people that dislike diligent and honest people.
或是有许多人 看不惯他人正经八百的样子
Perhaps they played a prank on someone they didn't like
也许他们趁着酒意 想在宴会上稍作玩笑
by messing with their alcohol at the party.
就对着不顺眼的人 拿他的酒瓶来恶作剧
And if that person continues drinking without noticing,
然而对方却像没事一般喝个不停
they might keep adding more salt until they do notice.
他们就很有可能想着 干脆加到对方发现为止
-Gaoshun. -Yes.
-高顺 -在
Yes, sir.
遵命
I'm such a coward.
我真是卑鄙啊
At this point, I'm basically telling them who the culprit is.
将线索给到了这种程度 几乎就跟直接指出犯人是谁一样
I don't want to be the direct cause of anyone's punishment.
但我不想成为任何人受罚的直接原因
Sorry about that.
真不好意思
-You helped a lot. -Thank you.
-你帮了很大的忙 -不会
An obsidian tassel…
黑曜石流苏…
Is he in mourning?
他在服丧吗？
He must've been a great man.
那位是如此优秀的人物吗？
Yes. He took care of me when I was young.
嗯 小时候受过他的照顾
He looks like a regular young man.
看起来就像个寻常的青年
I guess he's human after all.
他毕竟也是个凡人啊
Oh, I almost forgot.
对了
-This is a gift of thanks. -A gourd?
-这是谢礼 -葫芦？
Yes, although it's different from what you had yesterday.
对 虽然跟昨天的不一样
It's alcohol?
是酒吗？
-Yeah. Don't get caught, all right? -Yes, sir.
-小心点喝 别被发现了 -是
Thank you!
十分感谢
You don't look that grateful to me.
看起来不像是道谢的表情呢
You think so?
是这样吗？
I think you should be getting back to work.
比起这个 您是不是该回去认真工作了？
I knew it, he's slacking off from work.
看这个反应 果然在偷懒啊
You should finish before it starts piling up.
趁着公务还没堆积如山 快点做完如何？
I have been working…
我有认真工作啊…
-What kind of work? -For example, I'm working on a bill.
-怎么个认真法？ -说起来 有这样一个法案
They say they should prevent the youth from over-drinking,
为了防止年轻人沉溺于饮酒
and they should set an age limit.
应该订出饮酒的年龄限制
Huh?
什么？
The law states that drinking is prohibited until you're 20.
说是要规定二十岁以前禁止饮酒
Sir Jinshi…
壬氏大人…
Make sure that never passes, all right?
请千万别让这个法案通过
That's out of my hands.
不晓得呢 这也不是我自己能决定的
Sir Jinshi!
壬氏大人
Doctor!
太医
It's this way!
在这儿
A ghost!
出…出现了！
You're lucky it was winter.
幸好现在是冬天
The body is in a good state considering that she drowned.
虽然是溺死的 但尸体的状况算很好
How can you stare?
你居然敢盯着看…
-Where was the body found? -She was floating in an outside moat.
-尸体在哪儿发现的？ -漂浮在外侧的护城河上
From her clothes, she must be a servant in the rear palace.
从衣着看来 应该是后宫的婢女没错
I see. That's why they called for the old man.
原来如此 所以才会来叫大叔…
And the quack doctor. The one doing the autopsy is like this…
然而该验尸的医官却是这副德性 真是没救的庸医阿
-Miss, can you look for me? -No.
-小姑娘 你能代替我看看吗？ -不行
I've been told not to touch the body.
有人叫我不准碰尸体
That's surprising.
那还真让人意外
-Sir Jinshi! -How do you do, Sir Jinshi.
-壬氏大人 -壬氏大人 近来可好？
Looks like you're used to dead bodies.
你看到尸体很镇定呢
I've seen them many times.
这场面看惯了
The back alleys of the pleasure district are a lawless area.
花街的深处就是三不管地带嘛
Why can't you touch the body?
为什么不能碰尸体？
I've been instructed by my apothecary master.
教我药学的师父告诉我的
-Because it's bad luck? -No…
-是怕触霉头吗？ -不是…
Because humans can also become "ingredients for medicine."
因为人也可以成为“药材”
I'm sure with your curious nature,
好奇心旺盛的你
you will start robbing graves if you try it even once.
一旦碰过了尸首 肯定连盗墓都干得出来吧
Never cross that line, okay?
所以绝对不可以跨过那条线
Yes, sir.
知道了
I see. That makes sense.
原来如此
That's rude of them.
真失礼的反应
Doctor, could you please take a look?
太医 能请你好好地看一下吗？
Yes, sir…
我知道了
Geez…
天啊…
She's tall, wearing hard, wooden shoes.
个子很高 穿着坚硬的木鞋
Bandaged on one foot with red fingertips…
一脚缠着绷带 指尖泛红
It must've been cold inside the water.
水里一定很冷吧
The girl was a Food Service maid,
那个姑娘是御膳房的婢女
and had been working as usual yesterday.
到昨天都还如常在工作
The guard speculates she climbed the fence last night
卫兵的见解是她在昨夜爬上围墙
and jumped into the moat.
跳进了护城河
In other words, it was suicide by jumping.
也就是说 她是投水自尽的
Suicide by jumping…
投水自尽…
-What do you think? -I don't know if it's suicide or not.
-你觉得呢？ -是否自杀还不能确定
But I think it was impossible to accomplish on her own.
但我认为她一个人是办不到的
What do you mean?
此话怎讲？
There were no ladders along the wall,
围墙上没有梯子
and there were no climbing tools either.
也没有任何攀爬工具
The castle walls of the rear palace are four times my height.
后宫城墙的高度是我身高的四倍
So you need a tool to climb.
所以没有工具是不可能的
Usually, yes.
通常是这样
Strictly speaking,
严格说来
it's possible to climb the walls without tools.
不用工具爬上去是有可能的
Do you remember the ghost incident from before?
您还记得先前的幽灵作祟吗？
-The one with Concubine Fuyou? -Yes.
-芙蓉妃的那件事？ -是的
I wondered how Concubine Fuyou climbed the outer walls,
我很疑惑芙蓉妃是如何爬上外墙的
so I performed a close investigation of the castle walls.
所以就仔细地调查了城墙
There, I found a protrusion that must've been used
然后我发现了突出的砖头
by the carpenters.
我想那应该是工匠用过的机关
But it would be difficult for most women to climb,
但大部分女子应该都难以办到吧
let alone a woman with bound feet like that maid…
更别提像那位婢女一样的缠足之人了
Foot binding is based on the belief that the smaller your feet, the more beautiful.
缠足是认为脚越小就越美的风俗
It's not performed on all women, but I often see women
并不是所有的女子都会这么做 但在后宫偶而会看到
with a distinctive walking style in the rear palace.
有独特走路姿态的女子
So if it's not suicide,
如果不是自杀的话
you're saying it's murder?
就是他杀的意思？
I don't know about that.
这还不确定
But I am sure that she was alive when she fell into the moat.
但我确定她掉进护城河里时还活着
She must've kept scratching the fence to climb up.
她可能为了爬上围墙 而拼命抠抓墙壁吧
The fingertips on the body were red from bleeding.
尸体的指尖是被血染红的
So, was it suicide or murder?
是自杀 还是他杀…
I would never consider taking my own life.
我的话 是绝对不会有寻死的想法
I'd never want to get murdered either.
也绝对不会想被别人杀死
Once you die, you can't test for any medicine or poison.
一旦死了 就无法再尝试任何药物或毒物了
But if I were to die…
但如果我想寻死的话…
What are you thinking?
你在想什么？
About what poison I'd use if I were to die.
如果我想寻死的话 要用哪种毒药
-What? You mean to die? -Not at all.
-什么？你想寻死吗？ -没有那回事
But you never know when you could die, right?
但人的死期是无法预测的
Even if you don't wish it, someone's ill wishes could
即使不想死 但某人加诸的恶意
lead to an unwanted death.
也可能让自己死得不甘不愿
Like Sir Kounen.
就如浩然大人的事情
You never know when death will visit you.
谁都无法预测死亡何时到来
You cannot defeat fate, no matter what…
命运是无法抵抗的
-Sir Jinshi. -What is it?
-壬氏大人 -怎么了？
If you are ever going to execute me,
如果某天我要被处刑
can you kill me with poison?
可以请您赐毒给我吗？
Why would that happen?
怎么会有那种事？
If I ever make a mistake and offend anyone,
如果我犯了错或冒犯了某人
I'm sure you will be the one to punish me.
处分我的应该会是壬氏大人吧？
Have I already offended him?
我已经冒犯到他了吗？
I'm sorry. I got carried away.
对不起 我太得意忘形了
I won't complain even if it's death by hanging or beheading.
无论是绞刑或是斩首 我都不会有任何怨言的
I'm saying, why would that happen?
所以为什么会变成那样？
Because I'm a peasant.
因为我只是个平民
My life could be taken away by any small mistake.
如果犯了点小错 很可能马上就小命不保
I'd never do that.
我才不会做那种事
No matter what you will or won't do.
这不是会不会
It could happen.
而是能不能的问题
Looks like I shouldn't have said that.
我似乎说了些麻烦的话
If we're finished here, I'll be off.
如果没别的事 小的就先告退了
Later, I heard rumors that the dead maid was present
后来我听到风声说
at the poisoning incident at the garden party.
死去的婢女涉入了游园会的下毒事件
They even found a suicide note,
也找到了相关的遗书
and thus, the case was ruled a suicide and closed.
这次事件就以自杀落幕了
The reports from the other day are finally here.
那天的报告终于出来了
Two months since I ordered a search for a person with a burn on their arm.
我下令寻找手臂烧伤的人 已经过了两个月了
You took too much time.
你花太多时间了
I'm sorry, sir.
非常抱歉
So, who was it?
那么 到底是谁？
It was someone higher-ranked than we expected.
是 意外地是个大人物
Fengming, from The Garnet Pavilion.
柘榴宫的风明
She's the head lady-in-waiting for the Pure Concubine, Lady Ah-Duo.
淑妃阿多妃的侍女长
I see.
这样啊
You may leave.
你可以退下了
Concubine Ah-Duo…
阿多妃…
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集预告）
Next Episode, "Honey."
下一集 《蜂蜜》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：杨易